<u>Linkedin</u> | GitHub | Credly





Swetha Ramesh Leicester, UK | +44 7917582181 | swetha.ramesh1998@gmail.com

# **OBJECTIVE**

A motivated recent graduate with a master's in advanced computer science and 2 years of corporate experience, specializing in data analysis and visualization projects. An avid learner currently engaged in mastering innovative technologies to stay at the forefront of the field.

## **EDUCATION**

#### **University of Leicester**

Leicester, UK

## **MSc in Advanced Computer Science**

01.2023-06.2024

Core Modules: Big Data and Predictive Analytics, Data Driven Service design, Agile Cloud Automation, Internet, and cloud computing, Interaction Design and User Experience.

Grade: Distinction

# Atria Institute of Technology

Bengaluru, India

# **Information Science & Engineering CGPA**

07.2016-07.2020

Core Modules: Data Structures, Software Engineering and Testing, Object Oriented Concepts, Design and analysis of Algorithms, Cloud Computing, Python Programming, Machine Learning and Big Data Analytics. Grade: Merit

# WORK EXPERIENCE

# **Test Automation Analyst, IBM**

02.2021 to 11.2022

- Led the testing of AT&T's Enhanced Push-to-Talk (EPTT) application, validating its functionality and performance for real-time communication used by first responders.
- Employed Excel, Jira, Git, and Selenium to manage and automate 100+ test cases, enhancing test efficiency by 30%. Leveraged power BI for comprehensive test data analysis, driving a 25% improvement in the testing process.
- Collaborated cross-functionally to troubleshoot technical issues, driving a 20% improvement in software systems. Maintained comprehensive test data documentation and delivered technical support to end users.
- Integrated CI/CD pipelines using Jenkins to streamline test automation workflows, resulting in a 15% reduction in deployment times and quicker feedback loops.
- Participated in code reviews and continuous integration practices to ensure the reliability and scalability of automation scripts.

#### Intern, Atria IOT labs 10.2019 to 11.2019

- Developed an event reservation system using RFID tags with python, SQL and IoT technologies, collaborating on a 4-week project.
- Integrated IoT solutions using Python, improving system efficiency by 40% in a high-paced, collaborative team environment.

## Intern, Hindustan Aeronautics Limited (HAL)-

04.2018 to 05.2018

- Collaborated with the HAL IT Department to revamp the CRM and Payroll System, focusing on data management and system optimization and reduced processing time by 20%. Enhanced online presence and ERP functionality by utilizing .Net framework and SQL for web development.
- Acquired practical proficiency in people analytics within HR and finance systems for over 2000 employees, honing problem solving and critical thinking capabilities.

## **CERTIFICATIONS & SKILLS**

#### **Certifications:**

- **AWS** certified Cloud practitioner
- Microsoft certified Azure fundamentals
- Python for **Data Science**

- Python Basic issued by Hacker Rank
- **IBM Agile Explorer**

### Skills

Languages: Python, SQL, Java, C++.

- Python Libraries: Pandas, Numpy, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Plotly, Scikit-learn, NLTK, TextBlob.
- Tools: Docker, Kubernetes, Jenkins, Jira, Flourish.
- Data Transformation: Excel(Array Formulas, Data Manipulation), Power BI, Tableau
- Project Management: Jira, Git, SVN.
- IELTS overall score 8.5

# **PROJECTS**

# Dissertation: Sentiment Analysis of UK Train Services Using Twitter Data

- Implemented a project analyzing public sentiments toward UK Train Operating Companies (TOCs) using Twitter, employing NLP and machine learning techniques.
- Leveraged advanced tools and methods including Python (twscrape, WordCloud), Tableau, Flourish; Algorithms and Accuracy: Naïve Bayes (74.30%), Logistic Regression (76.32%), SVM (76.1%), GBM (71.4%), Random Forest(74.53%) and Decision Tree (67.2%). The comparison showed that Logistic Regression, SVM, and Random Forest are the best performers.
- Established that Logistic Regression leads with an accuracy of 76.32%, followed by SVM at 76.17%, with both models doing equally well across precision, recall, and F1-score criteria.
- Created data visualizations (word clouds, regional sentiment maps) using Python, Tableau and Flourish to interpret sentiment trends effectively.
- Conducted a user evaluation study to assess the visualization effectiveness, informing decision-making processes for TOCs and policymakers.

# Neighborhood Property Price Analysis and Predictive Modeling for Strategic Insights:

- Designed visualizations by employing **Matplotlib**, **Plotly**, **and Power** BI to examine, clean, and present intricate data-sets. Discovered detailed patterns like how property prices vary by neighborhood and change over time.
- Compared a basic linear regression model with a more advanced one that included methods like K-means clustering and random forest regression.
- Found that the advanced model performed better with an 87% accuracy and additionally translated the complex datasets into clear, actionable insights, demonstrating the ability to support strategic decision-making—skills applicable to optimizing marketing campaigns and evaluating performance metrics.

# Distributed Whiteboard Application on Azure:

- Led the collaborative development and deployment of a real-time, distributed whiteboard application on Azure, showcasing expertise in cloud architecture, application development, and seamless integration with **Azure Web PubSub**.
- Transformed a stand-alone application into a scalable and collaborative platform, while identifying areas for future enhancements in data persistence and scalability.

# Detection of tomato growth state and surveillance system using computer vision and IoT:

- Implemented an IoT and computer vision-powered data analytics system for monitoring tomato growth stages.
- Optimized irrigation practices using a Raspberry Pi, DHT sensor for environmental data collection, and Python's OpenCV
  for image processing and analysis, enabling data-driven decision-making through the correlation and modeling of visual
  and sensor data.
- Published In JETIR ISSN UGC Approved & 5.87 Impact Factor | Date of Publication: 2020-06-08.

# **OTHER EXPERIENCE**

- Student Mirror board student representative at the University of Leicester.
- Café Assistant at Sainsbury's Café.
- Volunteered 20+ hours per month at a non-profit café in Leicester, supporting community outreach and event planning.
- Volunteer at a local animal shelter in Bengaluru, India.